{"tossups": [{"question": "Emperor Wu Di of Han placed a monopoly on salt and this material. A pillar of this material was signed by King Chandra and notoriously resists corrosion. The Hittites created artifacts of this material. Abraham Darby created a method to create the \u201cpig\u201d type of this substance using coke instead of charcoal. and its \u201cwrought\u201d form was used to construct the Eiffel Tower. For ten points, name this metal whose use ended the Bronze Age.", "answer": "<b> iron</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During Europe\u2019s industrial era, the most popular history of this country was an account by botanist Engelbert Kaempfer. The 26 martyrs were crucified in this country. After the<em> San Felipe</em> was shipwrecked near this country, its leader closed off most of its ports to Spanish and Portuguese missionaries and forced its Christian population to become Kakure [ka-koo-ray], or hidden. For ten points, name this country where Christianity once flourished around Nagasaki.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this period, accused parties were ordered to prove their innocence by the Law of 22 Prairial, which strengthened the Law of Suspects. This period came to an end when the Battle of Fleurus helped trigger the Thermidorian Reaction against one of this period\u2019s leaders. The Committee of Public Safety took control during this period, which ended with Maximilien Robespierre\u2019s own execution. For ten points, name this year-long phase of the French Revolution in many political enemies were guillotined.", "answer": "<b> Reign of Terror</b> (or<b> The Terror</b> or La<b> Terreur</b>; prompt on the French Revolution) Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Scottish financier John Law advertised land claims along this river, triggering a bubble named after this river in the French court. A Native American culture named for this river constructed the mounds at Cahokia. Robert de La Salle claimed the entirety of this river\u2019s basin for France, and its northern reaches were explored by Jacques Marquette and Louis Jolliet. The French territory of Louisiana was centered around, for ten points, what river that empties into the Gulf of Mexico near New Orleans?", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In the originally planned climax of<em> Men in Black II</em>, these structures were to release a swarm of UFOs. A helicopter is caught in a web between these structures in an original trailer for the first Tobey Maguire <em>Spiderman</em> film. The 2008 film<em> Man on Wire</em> documents Philippe Petit\u2019s illegal 1974 walk between these structures on a high-wire. Several early 21st century films edited out, for ten points, what Manhattan buildings that were attacked on September 11th?", "answer": "<b> World Trade Center</b> 1 and/or 2 (accept<b> Twin Towers</b> and other descriptive answers of the two tallest bulidings in the<b> WTC</b> complex)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "The first site to establish this industry in the U.S. was the Beverly Manufactory. A man nicknamed\u201cthe traitor\u201d memorized the designs of British equipment used in this industry and recreated it in the U.S.; that man was Samuel Slater. The Waltham-Lowell system placed young girls in this industry in boardinghouses in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. The product of Eli Whitney\u2019s gin was used in, for ten points, what industry that converted cotton into shirts and pants?", "answer": "<b> textile</b> industry (accept<b> cloth</b>ing industry or<b> garment</b> industry; accept<b> cotton</b> industry before read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Hugh Trenchard is nicknamed the \u201cfather of\u201d this military force, which sustained heavy casualties in Bloody April during the Battle of Arras. The efforts of this military force prompted the declaration\u201cNever was so much owed by so many to so few.\u201d This force employed the Sopwith Camel during World War I and the Supermarine Spitfire during World War II. For ten points, name this military force that battled the Luftwaffe to defend cities like Coventry and London.", "answer": "<b> Royal Air Force</b> (or<b> RAF</b>; accept<b> Royal Flying Corps</b>; accept descriptions of the<b> air force</b> of the<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, or<b> British Air Force</b>, or similar; prompt on partial answers; do not prompt on British Army) Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer included movements titled \u201cThe Absence\u201d and \u201cThe Return\u201d in a piano sonata inspired by his patron Archduke Rudolph fleeing Vienna,<em> Les Adieux</em>. He wrote a set of 33 variations on a waltz he supposedly dismissed as a \u201ccobbler\u2019s patch.\u201d This composer of the<em> Diabelli Variations</em> also wrote a sonata \u201cquasi una fantasia\u201d that reminded Ludwig Rellstab of an object shining over Lake Lucerne. For ten points, name this German composer of<em> F\u00a8ur Elise</em> and the<em> Moonlight Sonata</em>.", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man once threw his alcoholic friend John Collins into a river when he refused to row a boat. This man founded an intellectual group known as either the Leather Apron Society or the Junto [jun-toh]. In Boston, this man used the pseudonym Silence Dogood to send letters to<em> The New-England Courant</em>; after he moved to Philadelphia, he switched newspapers to work on<em> The Pennsylvania Gazette</em>. For ten points, name this founding father who wrote and published<em> Poor Richard\u2019s Almanack</em>.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A character created by this author is nicknamed \u201cWe don\u2019t do that\u201d after he is punished for refusing to carry a rifle in a parade. This author devoted one chapter to each of 100 years in his book<em> My Century</em>. This author, who admitted to being a member of the Waffen-SS in his memoir<em> Peeling the Onion</em>, wrote a novel in which Oskar Matzerath refuses to grow past the age of three. For ten points, name this German author of<em> The Tin Drum</em>.", "answer": "Gunter<b> Grass</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these provinces boasted the largest Roman baths outside of Rome after Constantine renovated Augusta Treverorum. Imperial Roman influence in these provinces began when Domitius Ahenobarbus was summoned to aid the city of Massilia. This region, which was divided into the provinces of Belgica, Aquitania, and Celtica, was conquered when a circumvallation wall helped defeat the Averni tribe at Alesia. Julius Caesar conquered, for ten points, what ancient region in modern-day France?", "answer": "provinces of<b> Gaul</b> (or<b> Gallia</b>; accept<b> Gallia</b> Belgica; accept<b> Gallia</b> Narbonensis after\u201cDomitius\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man rebuked Henry Proctor, saying \u201cI conquer to save, you [conquer] to kill\u201d after their joint army perpetrated a massacre of prisoners at Fort Meigs. The New Madrid earthquake was interpreted by locals as a sign to join this man, whose death at the Battle of the Thames led to the dissolution of his tribal confederacy and its alliance with Great Britain. For ten points, name this chief of the Shawnee who fought the United States before and during the War of 1812 but was absent from the disastrous Battle of Tippecanoe.", "answer": "<b> Tecumseh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler was denounced as illegitimate by Pope Pius V in the bull<em> Regnans in Excelsis</em> after refusing to persecute minority religions. The use of fireships at Gravelines [grah-vel-een] allowed this ruler to stave off enemy invasion. While preparing for an imminent attack from the Spanish Armada, this ruler inspired the troops at Tilbury by claiming to possess the \u201cbody of a weak, feeble woman\u201d but the \u201cheart and stomach of a king.\u201d Anne Boleyn was the mother of, for ten points, what Virgin Queen of 16th century England?", "answer": "<b> Elizabeth I</b> (prompt on Elizabeth)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>While in office, this man vetoed the Rivers and Harbors Act for its high cost. Robert Todd Lincoln finished his service as Secretary of War under this president. This man was</b> <b>initially distrusted for being a (+)</b> <b>\u201cStalwart\u201d Republican and supporting patronage,</b> <b>but he broke with his old boss Roscoe Conkling by reversing that stance and passing the (*) </b> Pendleton Act to reform civil service. This man served as Vice President under a man who was assassinated by Charles Guiteau. For ten points, name this President who succeeded James Garfield.", "answer": "Chester Alan<b> Arthur</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>These people reached their golden age under Simeon I, who waged successful campaigns against their Khazar enemies. Scholars belonging to this ethnic group developed the first Cyrillic script. Krum, a ruler of these people, allegedly lined the (+) skull of Nikephoros I with silver and used it as a drinking cup. After losing the Battle of Kleidion, these people were supposedly blinded en masse by the Byzantine emperor Basil II, who then became known as a (*)</b> \u201cslayer\u201d of them. For ten points, name this nomadic European ethnic group, the namesake of a modern country whose capital is Sofia.", "answer": "<b> Bulgar</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During the disposal of this man\u2019s body, his assassins drove a Fiat truck into the Koptyaki forest only to realize they had only one shovel. This man received notice that Leonid Sednev</b> <b>would be leaving his entourage shortly before he was (+)</b> <b>moved into the basement of the</b> <b>Ipatiev House in Yekaterinburg. (*)</b> Anastasia was speculated to have survived the murder of this man and his family. Fearing the advancing White Army, the Bolsheviks executed, for ten points, what final Russian tsar?", "answer": "<b> Nicholas II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Tensions leading up to this event were heightened due to similar events at the Tele-Star, the Checkerboard, the Snake Pit, and the Sewer. In the aftermath of this event, Maria</b> <b>Ritter stated her second biggest fear was being shown in the newspaper (+)</b> <b>wearing her</b> <b>mother\u2019s dress. This event was described as the \u201cHairpin Drop Heard Around the World\u201dby the Mattachine Society. This event took place at an establishment owned by the (*) </b>Genovese crime family that operated without a liquor license. For ten points, name this 1969 riot in Greenwich [gren-itch] Village, New York that began with a police raid on the namesake gay bar.", "answer": "<b> Stonewall</b> Inn riots (accept equivalents for riot)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Samuel Sharpe led a revolt in this country against the UK during the Baptist War. This country\u2019s Cockpit Country was the home of the first of the Maroon Wars. An activist born</b> <b>in this country founded the (+)</b> <b>Black Star Line as part of his Back to Africa movement.</b> <b>Black Star Line as part of his Back to Africa movement.</b> <b>This country\u2019s Port Royal grew via frequent use by (*)</b> <b>This country\u2019s Port Royal grew via frequent use by (*)</b> pirates like Henry Morgan, but was rocked by a 1692 earthquake. Marcus Garvey was born in, for ten points, what Caribbean island country where earthquake survivors founded the city of Kingston?", "answer": "<b> Jamaica</b> Page 10", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Sugar production in this state was controlled by an oligopoly nicknamed the Big Five. Thalia Massie was raped in this state, after which her family members murdered</b> <b>a local boxer in retribution. During a battle in this state, (+)</b> <b>Chuichi Nagumo</b> <b>controversially did not order a third aerial strike. Japanese Internment in this state was limited, as (*) </b> one-third of its population in 1940 was Japanese. America entered World War II after a Japanese sneak attack on, for ten points, what state\u2019s port of Pearl Harbor?", "answer": "<b> Hawai\u2019i</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}